Welcome to today's דף, daf, it's דף כ. daf Chaf. And we
pick up at the bottom of יט עמוד ב Yud Tet Amud
Bet and we're dealing with the משנה Mishna which deals with moneys
that are found
and determining what their identity is and also finding pieces of meat
which is where the גמרא Gemara turns to and trying to figure
out which קרבן korban it's from or maybe if it's נבילה nevela
or if it's not a נבילה nevela and that the issue about
finding pieces of meat becomes the focus of the גמרא. Gemara. So
we pick up two lines from the bottom
last two words on the line on יט עמוד ב. Yud Tet
Amud Bet. רב נחת לתמן. Rav Nachas L'Saman. Rav went down over
there, presumably to בבל. Bavel. כי אתא רב לבבל Ki Asa Rav
LeBavel is a phrase in the גמרא Gemara in גיטין. Gittin. So
Rav made transition from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael to בבל. Bavel. He
sort of started a lot of the whole ישיבות Yeshivot in בבל.
Bavel. So anyway when Rav went down there, down to בבל, Bavel,
ירידה, Yerida,
חמזו מקילין, Chamzu Meikilin,
he saw them being lenient around issues about meat presumably found in
the hands of non-Jews or meat that was not observed and וחמיר
עליהון V'Chamir Aleihon and he was מחמיר machmir on them.
So this is right so Michael identifies this with the discussion in
the בבלי Bavli of בשר שנתעלם מן העין. basar she-nisalem min ha-ayin.
If there's a moment when you're not watching the meat that you
can't eat it now the גמרא Gemara's concern seems to be very
far-fetched about like if you don't look at it then somebody will
come and steal the piece of meat and replace it with another
one we're actually going to have that discussion here but it's interesting
to note here the background the background is he saw that they
were lenient and he was being מחמיר machmir which means that maybe
he was concerned about other things and therefore he was being overly
strict in a way that maybe does exceed what the normal types
of concerns would normally be maybe they were being overly lenient based
on some of the issues before about assuming that things were you
know if a non-Jew had it or if it was found on
the floor they would just ah it's probably כשר kosher and they
wouldn't be worried about the concerns that we had mentioned earlier about
the likelihood that maybe it did come from a טריפה treif source.
So because he maybe saw a general leniency he was going to
be he decided to be overly strict. Okay so that's interesting and
sort of giving the context of some of the discussion we're going
to see which does seem a little far-fetched but it might have
been in response to leniencies. So let's take a look.
Technically Rav Lai would be חומרא chumra though?
Yeah right right. I mean חומרא chumra's always a question about whether
it means adopting the stricter of the normal sort of דין din
positions or whether חומרא chumra is
about an additional stringency here the language certainly seems to be an
additional over stringency and let's take a look at how this continues.
חד בר נש אזל Chad bar nash azil a certain person was
going כ עמוד א. Chaf amud aleph. במשיזגא אטפיחתא בגו נהרא. BeMishchag
Afkifta Begona Hara. So he wanted to wash his I don't you
know the מפרשים meforshim here explain the phrase but I can't do
a word-for-word translation. He wanted to wash his meat by the river.
So Mishchag presumably means wash I do not I didn't I should
have looked up I didn't get a chance to what אטפיחתא afkifta
means presumably by context it means his meat. But anyway he wanted
to wash his meat by the river.
ואינשצא Ve'Inshetsa and it fell out of his hands. ואזל ליה Va'Azal
Lei and he ran after it.
חזר במזווניה Chazar by misvaneih then he wanted to take it again
like it washed it fell out of his hands it was washed
down the river he ran after it and he grabbed it back
was it in his sight the whole time?
It sounds like it it's not clear. אמר ליה רב Amar Lei
Rav so Rav who we just saw a second before was being
מחמיר machmir Rav said to him אסור לך assur lecha it's forbidden
to
you. דנאמר D'na'amar ההוא שטף נהרא ואייתי חורי דנבילה תחותיה. hahi shatif
nahara ve'aisi chauri denevela tachosai. I will say that one piece the
river washed away and this piece that you found floating twenty feet
down is another piece of meat that magically is exactly the same
size of your meat happens to be exactly twenty feet down the
river but who knows maybe it's a different piece of meat and
the river brought in its place and maybe that is נבילה. nevela.
Now that of course seems absurd right? And that's the גמרא Gemara's
discussion of בשר שנתעלם מן העין. basar she-nisalem min ha-ayin. If you're
not watching it for one second who knows what would have happened
to it in the interim. But again what we have is the
framing that this was in response to watching overly leniencies in this
area of the meat and its source and its identity.
And it's not like טומאה tumah is there?
Who's talking about טומאה? tumah? It's נבילה.
nevela. Oh נבילה nevela that just happened?
Maybe yes this piece of meat floated away the piece of meat
you dropped floated away and this piece that you find floating twenty
feet down the river just happens to be a piece of נבילה
nevela that looks just like your piece of meat. I say it
is absurd right? But that's
why the גמרא Gemara frames it as that he was מחמיר. machmir.
Okay so alright now we have another story like this. חד בר
נש Chad bar nash a certain man הוי מהלך בשוקא hvei mehalach
beshuka he was going in the marketplace טוען קופא toen kuppa he
was carrying a piece
of Some type of an animal, some type of a bird came
and חטפה מיניה chatafah minei and swooped down and grabbed the piece
of meat from him. וטלקיה v'talakei and dropped it.
חזר בתריה, chazar batrei, he ran after it and saw that a
piece of meat had been dropped.
חזא מסויניה, chaza misvneia, he wanted to go take it back and
thought, okay, this is my piece of meat. אמר ליה רב, amar
lei Rav, so Rav said to him, אסור לך, assur lach, forbidden.
דלמא אמר dilma amar because you can say, I would say, בשר
דנבילה הוה טעינא basar d'neveila hava teina that the bird before it
grabbed your piece of meat was carrying a piece of נבילה, neveila,
וטלקיה v'talakei and dropped it, ונסיב ההיא אחרינא גביה v'nasiv ha'hi achreina
gaveih and it took
the and it took your piece of meat in its place. So
therefore, you know, I'm sorry,
ונסב ההיא אחרינא v'nasav ha'hi achreina and it took your piece of
meat in its place. So therefore just because you took a piece
of meat and then you found that it had dropped a piece
of meat, who's to say the piece of meat that it dropped
is the same piece of meat that it took?
This means that you didn't really see if it had anything else
in it before, right?
Right. I mean, you know, who knows exactly what happened? He grabbed
a piece of meat, you ran after it, twenty feet later you
saw it dropped a piece of meat. Who knows? Were you checking
and looking at it every single second and saw? Okay, so again,
it's pretty fantastical to assume that that's what happened.
You'd have to say if like you went out and had a
piece of meat in your refrigerator, you come home, you see the
same piece of meat.
Okay, so there is an idea of being משומר meshumar or not,
you know, and there's שימור shimur or whatever.
Some necessarily say that, right?
Right.
Correct. Okay. Now גינאי, Ginai, which is the name apparently of a
river, שטיף זיקין. shatif zikin. Now we're moving from meat to wine.
Okay, so the river washed away some flasks of wine. אתא עובדא
קומי רבי יצחק ורבי אלעזר, ata uvda kumei Rabbi Yitzchak v'Rabbi Elazar,
came in front of Rabbi Yitzchak and Rabbi Elazar, ואמר יחכמון שפייא
קטריהון. v'amar yachkmon shapaya kitreihon.
Let the, remember if you remember the word יחכמון yachkmon before from
the word חכמה, chochmah, but it means to recognize. So let the
wine pourers or the wine sellers
recognize their identify their knots, you know, that they put on these
flasks. They had made special knots. And then if they can identify
their knots, then they can assume that it is theirs and then
they can go ahead and take it. So it sounds, you know,
is this more lenient than Rav? Or it's the same point, but
at least if you really have an identifying mark, that's a different
story. Okay, but it seems like generally without that, even, you know,
he would have... it would be a similar concern by wine that
Rav had by meat. נוקניקא, Nuknika,
so this is a type of like a, also like a flask
or, you know, a jug.
אשתכח בכנישתא דבולי, ishtachach b'chnishta d'Buli, was found in the synagogue of
בולי. Buli. Now some place the name of בולי Buli is a
place. Actually, בולי Buli is a word that refers to, I believe,
like an
administrative governing body. Thank you. Right. It's a Greek word, *Boule*. Like
פרוזבול. pruzbul.
Right. Well, exactly. So פרוזבול, pruzbul, some want to say actually does
come from the word of בולי, Buli, which is exactly that, which
is like the sort of the a Roman governing tax collecting body.
So anyway, so it might be like a
wealthy בית כנסת, Beis Knesses, a wealthy people, whatever it is. Anyway,
in this בית כנסת Beis Knesses certain of these of these jugs
of wine were found. אתא עובדא קומי רבי ירמיה, ata uvda kumei
Rabbi Yirmiyah, so it came in front of Rabbi Yirmiyah. אמר יחכמון
שקוריא עבידתהון. amar yachkmon sakuraya avidatehon.
So let the שקוריא, sakuraya, which means presumably those that made the
marks on it, recognize their work, their handiwork. If they can recognize
their distinguishing marks, then they can assume it's theirs and take it.
The craftsmen or the people that actually handled the wine, but made
like, you know, personal marks to identify it as theirs. Okay, now
so that's wine, which indicates a, you know, which indicates a similar
concern, but at least in these stories, at least we allowed for
the possibility of reclaiming it, right? Presumably would it be true by
the meat story as well? If you had it in a package
and you recognized the mark, presumably yes. גדי צלי, Gdi t'zli, a
roasted goat, אשתכח באסטרטיה
דגופתא, ishtachach b'istratya d'Gufta, was found in the like *stratyan platya*, words
familiar in the בבלי, Bavli, right? Which are actually again Greek words
which means a *stratya* is a like
a major road and a *platya* like a what's the word? Plaza,
right. Exactly. And a *stratya*, what would be a word we have
now based on *stratya*? Estrada. Estrada. Street, I guess. Right. Okay. There
you go. Okay. Although *stratya*, *stratya*, anyway. Okay. Okay. So anyway, in
this street they found a roasted goat in the street of גופתא.
Gufta. והתירוה v'hitirua
and they made a permissibility. So now in contrast to Rav, where
it's like oh my God, you know, you ran after the meat
and two seconds later he said it's אסור, assur, here they just
found a roasted goat lying around in the street and they said
it was permissible. Okay, why? משום שני דברים mishum shnei d'varim meaning
they
not that there were two factors to make it permissible but they
permitted two different concerns. Number one, it's a found object, meaning who
says you can take it? Maybe you have to go looking for
the owner, who allows you to take it? ומשום רוב מהלכי דרכים
umishum rov mahallchei drachim
based on the most of the people who go in the street
who were Jewish, you can assume that it was kosher. So A,
you can assume it's kosher and B, you can take it for
yourself. And now we're going to explain it out. Explain, משום מציאה
mishum metziah because of lost objects, דתניא detanya we learned in a
ברייתא, Braitah, המוצא מיד הארי hamotzei miyad ha'ari if you save an
object that was seized or was about to be devoured by a
lion, ומיד הגייס umiyad hagayis or a marauding troops, ומשטופה של ים
meshutoofah shel yam ומשלוליתו של נהר umeshaloolito shel nahar from like an
outcropping by the ocean or by the river, something was about to
be washed away and you saved it.
מאסטרטיה גדולה ומפלטיא גדולה me'istratia gedolah u'mipaltia gedolah from a major street
you saved it from the middle of like,
you know, of Broadway or of you know or of the FDR
and or from the middle of אסטרטיה גדולה istratia gedolah you in
the middle of Times Square you found something. Okay, so in all
those cases, הרי אלו שלו harei elu shelo you can keep it.
You don't have to worry about a סימן, siman, you don't have
to worry if the בעלים be'alim had יאוש. ye'ush. Why? מפני שהבעלים
מתייאשין מהן. mipnei shehabe'alim mityashin mehen. If you drop your wallet in
Times Square, that's it. You're not going to look for it anymore.
You assume it's gone. Okay? So in all these cases you basically
just have יאוש ye'ush immediately and therefore if anybody finds it, they
can keep it. So number one, you can keep it for yourself.
Now, משום רוב מהלכי דרכים mishum rov mahallchei drachim and as far
as the most of the of the passersby, the people that go
in that street, משום שחיטת נכרי mishum shechitat nochri you don't have
to be concerned that it is that it is שחיטה shechted by
a non-Jew, you can assume that this is Jewish meat. Now, what's
quite fascinating is a couple of things. Number one is, you know,
totally against רב Rav with these crazy concerns, but even beyond that,
you know, you could have imagined the גמרא Gemara say okay, רוב
מהלכי דרכים rov mahallchei drachim but number one, like why would somebody
drop it? Why wouldn't they be careful about it? Maybe the reason
they're not being careful is a signal that it's not kosher, you
know, or even if it's kosher שחיטה shechitah by a Jewish שוחט,
shochet, maybe it's a טרפה. treifah. But again, the גמרא Gemara here
going back to the משנה Mishnah and going back to the earlier
discussions is willing to use sort of the normal likelihoods of things
to assume the status and allow you to eat this meat and
not concern that it might be a נבילה neveilah might be a
טרפה treifah which is very much again against the חומרות chumrot of
רב Rav that we had just read a minute ago.
Was that what was in the conference yesterday, right?
איסורא ואכלא? issura ve'achla? Right, exactly. Okay. By the way, it's also
interesting just the terminology because when because the meaning רוב מהלכי דרכים
rov mahallchei drachim is the reason to be lenient. It's not the
category we're being lenient about. The category we're being lenient about is
כשרה נבילה ksherah neveilah whereas the issue of משום מציאה mishum metziah
is the category we're being lenient about. The reason to be lenient
is because it was in a big public space. So it's a
little funny the way it phrases that.
Wasn't רב Rav a market inspector?
That one
I don't remember exactly.
One of them was a market.
You could be right. I don't remember that.
Okay.
Now, the גמרא Gemara says like this, similar story.
I'm sorry, wait, we didn't finish this. ואשתכח ve'ishtakach מן דבי רבי
min d'vei Rabbi and lo and behold it was discovered afterwards that
it had actually originated in the house of רבי. Rabbi. So you
knew that relying on the fact that it was kosher was actually
legitimate. It turned out that it all was it all actually was
kosher meat. So
not only did it bracket רב Rav and end with a more
lenient הלכתי halachic position, it actually then underscored and said and the
facts bore out that that was correct. Okay. Now, they didn't have
to return it because it was יאוש. ye'ush. Right. עיגולא דגופנא igoola
d'goofna now similarly a like a circle a pressed you know like
wheel they call it, right? A wheel of
גבינה gvina
was found in the like inn of לוי. Levi. והתירוהו משום שני
דברים ve'hitiroohu mishum shnei d'varim and they permitted it for two aspects
were permitted. משום מציאה mishum metziah they didn't have to worry of
returning it to the owner because apparently לוי Levi did a very
good business and it was a high throughput maybe it was more
like a you know it was a bar and there were people
going in at all times. And ומשום רוב מהלכי דרכים umishum rov
mahallchei drachim they didn't have to be concerned about the origin that
it was גבינת עובדי כוכבים gvinat ovdei kochavim because most of the
people that went through it were Jewish. משום מציאה דתניא mishum metziah
detanya same thing as before, המוצא מיד הגייס מיד הארי משטופה של
ים ומשלוליתו של נהר מאסטרטיה גדולה ומפלטיא גדולה הרי אלו שלו מפני
שהבעלים מתייאשין מהן. hamotzei miyad hagayis miyad ha'ari meshutoofah shel yam umeshaloolito
shel nahar me'istratia gedolah u'mipaltia gedolah harei elu shelo mipnei shehabe'alim mityashin
mehen. If you find it in a place where either it was
gonna definitely be lost because it was gonna be eaten by a
lion or washed away or because there were so many people that
the owner would figure I'll never get it back then you just
assume יאוש ye'ush and you can keep it. And ומשום רוב מהלכי
דרכים ומשום גבינת עובדי כוכבים umishum rov mahallchei drachim umishum gvinat ovdei
kochavim we don't have to be concerned that it's non-Jewish cheese because
most of the people were Jewish. ואשתכח מדרבי אלעזר ברבי יוסי ve'ishtakach
mid'Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Yosei and lo and behold it was discovered that
it actually came from the house of רבי אלעזר ברבי יוסי Rabbi
Elazar b'Rabbi Yosei or owned by רבי אלעזר ברבי יוסי Rabbi Elazar
b'Rabbi Yosei so you see. so you see it was good that
we relied on the fact that it was kosher cheese, it actually
turned out to be such. אמר רבי מני קומי רבי יוסי. Amar
Rabi Mani kumei Rabi Yose. So Rabbi Mani said in front of
Rabbi Yose, והנן חמינן ve'anan chamian okay that's all very nice in
theory, but we see רבנן rabanan מחריז. machriz. Now it's fascinating, it
does not end with a חומרא chumra about if you decide if
I told you the next statement is going to be more מחמיר
machmir you would have assumed it's more מחמיר machmir to go back
to רב, Rav, say oh we won't eat that stuff. But actually
it says no, no, no, we see people are more מחמיר machmir
to return it. Okay, about the מציאה metziah idea. Technically, now how
did because look if you think about it how'd they know the
meat was רבי'ס, Rebbe's, how did they know the cheese was, who
was it, was רבי אלעזר ברבי יוסי? Rabi Elazar berabbi Yose? Because
presumably it had a סימן siman on it, but you didn't have
to return it because even with a סימן siman if you assume
you'll never get it back and you're ייאוש yei'ush the next person
can keep it. So he says yeah, but we know, we see
when this happens and people find something in Times Square they're going
to announce that they found a wallet, they're going to try to
return it. They're more, they're more מחמיר machmir than that in terms
of returning the objects. Okay, והנן חמינן רבנן מחריזין. ve'anan chamian rabanan
machrizin.
So that's what רב מני Rav Mani said to רבי יוסי. Rabi
Yose. אמר ליה, Amar lei, רבי יוסי Rabi Yose said back to
him, את אין הויסטה משתכח לא נסיבת. at in havista mishtakach lo
nasivat.
You, if you would have found such a wallet I know you
wouldn't keep it for yourself, but you should know רבי יונה אבוך,
Rabi Yona abuch, but רבי יונה Rabi Yona your father, לא אמר
כן. lo amar kein. He didn't say that you couldn't keep it.
אלא אמר, ela amar, he said, הלואי כד נשכח halevai kad nishkach
you know,
I only wish that if I find a wallet, נשכח מן פיוסה
ולגוא nishkach min piyusa ulegav I'll find it from פיוסה Piyusa which
is I don't know some type of a major thoroughfare, I'll find
it in a major thoroughfare. I hope if I find a wallet
with a million dollars it doesn't have the person's driver's license in
it is basically what he's saying. I hope I'll find it in
a place that I'll be able to keep it. So you want
to be very פרום frum but your father indicated that he's happy
to rely on the הלכה halacha and to keep it if he's
entitled to keep it. So the גמרא Gemara says, ואפילו כן ve'afillu
kein nevertheless, אשכח ולא נסיב ashkach velo nasiv if he found and
he didn't take it for himself. So there's a question who found?
Did the father, the father said this in theory like, but you
know, okay you think oh I'd love to find a lottery ticket
and be able to keep it, but in reality he was much,
you know, when, when, when the facts are on the ground he
wanted to make sure the real owner got it back. Okay, that's
I think a nice way to end it. Some say this end
of the story is he heard what his father did and he
didn't care, he still wanted to go ahead and return it when
he found things, what his father, what his father did. So I
gotta tell you it's quite fascinating because again in the בבלי, Bavli,
right, it's hard to imagine you would ever get this story. In
the בבלי Bavli it would always be I can't live up to
how great my father was. Right, like the בבלי Bavli talks about,
you know, waiting between meat and milk. It says my father, he
says I'm like חלא, chala, my father was חמרא, chamra, my father
he would eat meat, he wouldn't eat milk for twenty-four hours, me
נבך nebach I wait just until the next meal. And that's where
we get the whole idea of six hours from that one statement.
Okay, but here you see that the father actually was more, the
son was being more פרום frum than the father. So number one,
that's you know, fascinating. And number two, it's also I think very
powerful because you know, if you think where most people are they
would be more א, aleph, if you were going to be more
מחמיר machmir on one of these two things most people's inclination would
be to be more מחמיר machmir on the כשרות kashrut aspect, not
on the returning aspect. And number two, if you talked about a
difference between theory and practice you would talk about, you know, okay,
you know, like, maybe in principle I פסקן pasken that it's אסור,
assur, but like in practice I'm going, my יצר הרע yetzer hara
is going to get the better of me. Whereas here you get
the exact reverse, right? In principle he פסקנס paskens that it's מותר,
muttar, but when it comes to real people and real objects that
they really own he's going to actually actually be more מחמיר machmir
in practice in terms of getting the object back.
So it's an interesting פרדיגמה, paradigma, like what's the criterion for being
more פרום, frum, dieting on the meat or doing the הכרזה hachrazah
to return.
Yeah, exactly, yeah.
But what's interesting is and, you know, based, based on this, it
seems that we've really bracketed רב, Rav, right? Totally.
The ירושלמי Yerushalmi totally brackets רב, Rav, the בבלי Bavli totally, right?
Well, that's רב Rav moved to בבל. Bavel. And anyway it was
in בבל, Bavel, remember also that the בבלי Bavli said, the, even
the ירושלמי Yerushalmi here's saying when רב Rav went to בבל, Bavel,
רב Rav was more מחמיר machmir because he saw them being lenient
over there, which means that the ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael tradition would
remain the same.
But yeah, we usually remain with the בבלי Bavli for...
Well yeah, I mean there's a question of how do we rule
about בשר שנתעלם מן העין basar shenisallem min ha'ayin nowadays especially now,
you know, to what degree again like this גמרא Gemara you have
סימנים simanim and so on, but look, there's a lot more חומרות
chumrot as you can imagine around השגחות hashgachot for meat restaurants and
non-meat. Some people want to quote the whole sources of בשר שנתעלם
מן העין, basar shenisallem min ha'ayin, but the reality is it's not
those the technical concerns of בשר שנתעלם מן העין, basar shenisallem min
ha'ayin, it's more the degree of טריפות treifot that you can get
by meat is much greater than the types of טריפות treifot you
normally get in מילכיג milchig restaurants. And number two, the יצר הרע
yetzer hara in terms of the financial benefits are much greater. But
you know, but
so sometimes you hear בשר שנתעלם מן העין basar shenisallem min ha'ayin
discussed in those contexts, but it's usually a misnomer. All right let's
take a look at the next משנה. Mishna. גבינה דקה, Gvina dakah,
וזהו vezehu
I assume is
different than what we mean by גבינת עובד כוכבים? gvinat oved kochavim?
No. Why? It was really בשר בחלב basar bechalav because they חשש...
chashash... No, no, no, it means גבינת עובד כוכבים gvinat oved kochavim
in the משנה Mishna of עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara. No, no, but
about... Okay, let's look at our משנה. mishnah. בהמה שנמצאת מירושלים ועד
מגדל עדר. beheimah shenimtzeit miyerushalayim ve'ad migdal eder. So we're back to
identifying objects and their sources and their identity. So, before we talked
about finding pieces of meat, and you might remember that if you
find meat in ירושלים, yerushalayim, you assume it's שלמים shlamim meat. However,
you have to burn it because it might be נותר. nosar. Okay,
and then questions about is it in limbs and is it in
chopped up pieces, etc. This is talking now not about finding pieces
of meat, it's talking about finding the animals. בהמה שנמצאת מירושלים ועד
מגדל עדר. beheimah shenimtzeit miyerushalayim ve'ad migdal eder. You find an animal
what, live animals, yes, okay, you find a live animal anywhere in
ירושלים yerushalayim until מגדל עדר, migdal eder, which is like a nearby
village, וכמידתה לכל רוח, uchmidasah lechol ruach, and that circumference around ירושלים,
yerushalayim, so within a certain amount of distance on the outskirts of
ירושלים. yerushalayim. So you still assume it's from ירושלים yerushalayim because, you
know, as opposed to pieces of meat, animals do walk on their
own, so therefore it could have started in ירושלים yerushalayim and walked
out. And again, we're going to assume that most of the meat
in ירושלים yerushalayim has a קרבן korban type of a purpose. So
when it was the meat, we assumed it would only be a
possible עולה olah if it's on the grounds of the בית המקדש.
beis hamikdash. But here, you can have עולות olos outside of the
grounds because you sanctified it as an עולה olah and you didn't
just get and you didn't get a chance to bring it yet.
So by the animal case, we have to be concerned that it's
not that even out of the בית המקדש beis hamikdash but in
ירושלים yerushalayim and its environs, it might be an עולה. olah. So,
זכרים עולות, zecharim olos, the male animals we assume are an עולה
olah because males can be an עולה, olah, ונקבות, unekeivos, the females,
which cannot be an עולה, olah, are זבחי שלמים. zivchei shlamim. Again,
the assumption that things will be שלמים shlamim because everybody's using their
מעשר שני ma'aser sheini money and so on to buy שלמים. shlamim.
Now the גמרא gemara is going to ask the obvious question: if
the assumption in the previous משנה mishnah is that there's so much
שלמים shlamim meat going on, so why don't we assume that the
males are also שלמים? shlamim? A male animal can be a שלמים,
shlamim, can be male or female.
Okay, so we'll see about that in the גמרא. gemara. Yeah. Did
most people wait till the last minute, in which case then...
Right, I mean, that's a good question too. Right, that's a good
question too. Why do we assume that people, you know, that סתם
stam animals, it's one thing once it's in the state of meat,
but if it's in a state of animals, why do we assume,
you know, did the חזל chazal ever go around and do a
survey and try to figure out exactly what's like the distribution of
live animals, how many are sanctified or aren't sanctified? It's a very
good question. It's a very good question. And again, it might just
be a חומרא. chumrah. We have to be מחמיר machmir and assume,
but we saw before we were willing to be lenient and assume
something was חולין chullin rather than מעשר שני ma'aser sheini if that's
where the likelihood lay. So I really don't know the answer. רבי
יהודה אומר הראוי לפסחים rabbi yehuda omer hara'uy lapsachim and this, I
think, is a question you asked yesterday, Micah. פסחים, pesachim, קודם הרגל
שלשים יום, kodem haregel shloshim yom, if something could be a פסח,
pesach, like it's a sheep or goat and it's less than a
year old and it's male and it's within thirty days around before
פסח, pesach, it's after פורים, purim, then we're going to assume it's
a פסח. pesach. That's most likely what those animals will be, okay,
at that time of the year. בראשונה היו ממשכנין את מוצאה, barishonah
hayu memashkenin es motzah, now here's a fascinating sort of shift into
questions about special תקנות takanos that חזל chazal did. בראשונה היו ממשכנין
את מוצאה, barishonah hayu memashkenin es motzah, it should be מוצאה, motza'ah,
or מוצאה, motzo'ah, probably מוצאה, motza'ah, עד שהוא מביא נסכיה. ad shehu
mevi nesacheha. So let's say you found this wandering animal and it's
male, so I have to assume it's an עולה. olah. If it's
female, assume it's a שלמים. shlamim. So I'm going to be a
good guy, I mean, okay, it's a big שלעפ schlep to the
בית המקדש, beis hamikdash, but, you know, it's not such a שלעפ,
schlep, I mean you're in ירושלים, yerushalayim, but okay, I'll take out
an hour, I'll bring it to the בית המקדש, beis hamikdash, I
give it to the כהנים, kohanim, I found this animal, here, go
ahead, bring it as an עולה. olah. So the כהנים kohanim say,
that's very nice, where's the נסכים? nesachim? I say, where's the what?
They say, well, where's the נסכים? nesachim? You know, you gotta bring
נסכים nesachim with an עולה. olah. So now I gotta spend twenty
bucks of my own money to bring the נסכים nesachim for this.
So originally they said, tough luck, you found it, you're the one
now bringing it, so you're the one who's going to have to
pay for the נסכים, nesachim, which is astounding, it's like it's not
even my קרבן. korban. And then not so much would they just
ask me, היו ממשכנין, hayu memashkenin, they would actually take my property
as collateral. They might go ahead and pay for the נסכים, nesachim,
but they'd want to be paid back, and they'd take my property
as collateral until I paid them back. So guess what the result
of that was? חזרו להיות מניחין אותה ובורחין. chazru lihyos manichin osah
uvorchin. So then they said, oh my God, it's an animal! They
ran in the opposite direction. Who wants to do that? התקינו בית
דין שנסכיה באין משל ציבור. hitkinu beis din shenesacheha ba'in mishel tzibur.
So then they said, if somebody turns in a found animal, we'll
bring the נסכים nesachim out of communal funds. So now, of course,
you wonder someone says, ooh, so next time I bring my עולה
olah to the בית המקדש, beis hamikdash, I'll just tell them it's
a found animal. Yeah, exactly. No, if somebody else's עולה, olah, you
can't use as yours, you know, you can't transfer the once it's
been sanctified. Okay. אמר רבי שמעון שבעה דברים התקינו בית דין. amar
rabbi shimon shivah devarim hitkinu beis din. Now that we're talking about
special תקנות takanos that they made, we're going to talk about seven
תקנות. takanos. Some are in a similar type of a category. שבעה
דברים התקינו בית דין, shivah devarim hitkinu beis din, seven things בית
דין beis din established, obviously more, but seven of a category. וזה
אחד מהם, ve-zeh echad me-hem, and what was one we just listed
was one of them, and here are some others. נכרי ששלח עולתו
ממדינת הים, Nochri she-sholach olato mi-medinat ha-yam, ושלח עמה נסכים. ve-sholach imah
nesachim. So a similar, if a non-Jew sent a קרבן, korban, non-Jews
are allowed to bring קרבנות korbanot to the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash.
So he sent it from overseas. He's not here right now that
we can ask him to give anything else. So he sent it.
If he happened to know the law and our ritual and sent
with it נסכים nesachim or money for the נסכים, nesachim, קרבין משלו,
kerevin mishelo, we'll bring the נסכים nesachim from his funds. ואם לאו,
Ve-im lav, if he sent the קרבן korban and he didn't give
any money, קרבין משל ציבור, kerevin mi-shel tzibbur, we're not going to
reject the קרבן. korban. We all know the famous story about how
the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash got destroyed, but anyway, whoever this person
is, we will bring it from משל ציבור. mi-shel tzibbur. But notice
that's a non-Jew. If a Jew sent it long distance, presumably, I
don't know if we would wait to bring the קרבן, korban, but
presumably we would demand to be repaid. That's your קרבן korban you're
bringing, you're going to pay for the נסכים. nesachim. But if it's
a non-Jew and he's not here and around to ask him, we'll
supply the נסכים. nesachim. If he is around then we would right.
But say I don't know what we would do but anyway there'd
be more options. וכן גר שמת, Ve-chen ger she-met, if a convert
died, which is always an interesting scenario to discuss because כקטן שנולד
דמי, ke-katan she-nolad dami, so if he doesn't have any kids then
all of his property, there's no heirs. So גר שמת והניח זבחים
ger she-met ve-hiniach zevachim and he leaves over unbrought sacrifices, animals that
were sanctified. אם יש לו נסכים, Im yesh lo nesachim, if he
has in his estate נסכים, nesachim, money for the נסכים, nesachim, קרבין
משלו, kerevin mishelo, we draw on the estate for that. Now of
course what's fascinating is that one minute, who took over the estate?
Right? Because the גמרא Gemara always deals with the case the גר
ger died so it's a free-for-all, whoever can run to the property
and seize it, it's הפקר hefker gets it. So either nobody took
it and then the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash might as well take
over the entire estate, or somebody else already seized it so then
it's now the other person's property. So it's not exactly clear to
me how that works out, but somehow let's assume somebody else seized
it and nevertheless we will assume that we have some lien on
that property and we'll collect it. ואם לאו, Ve-im lav, but here's
the real תקנה, takkanah, the תקנה takkanah is if there is nobody
to pay for the נסכים nesachim but we still have the גר's
ger קרבן, korban, so that's obviously analogous to the previous situation, then
קרבין משל ציבור, kerevin mi-shel tzibbur, we bring it from communal funds.
So three types of cases now we bring from communal funds. It's
not your קרבן korban but it was wandering around and you brought
it, number one. Number two is it's from a non-Jew who's not
here. And number three is it's from a גר ger who's not
here and there's no heir to deal with. So there's no owner
in all three cases, the owner is not present. And it's not
really considered to be accessible. In one case we don't know, in
one case it's a non-Jew ממדינת הים mi-medinat ha-yam we're not going
to bother with that case, and in one case he's certainly not
around. What if someone dies locally and all heirs are overseas? Okay,
so that's an interesting question, maybe that would be similar. How about
if somebody sends a קרבן korban from overseas? There's an assumption that
if it's a Jew who's sending the קרבן korban even from overseas
at least we'll keep the debt on the books. Maybe we won't
run after him but at least we'll keep the debt on the
books. Okay. וכן, ve-chen, okay, so that's that. ותנאי בית דין הוא.
U-tenai beit din hu. Now, okay, that's it. ותנאי בית דין הוא.
U-tenai beit din hu. Now notice here, before we called it a
תקנה takkanah and now we're having this תנאי בית דין. tenai beit
din. תנאי בית דין Tenai beit din is one thing to just
say where the funds are going to come from. תנאי בית דין
Tenai beit din is a phrase that we've used to deal with
how we manipulate קדושה kedusha to allow it to play by our
rules. ותנאי בית דין הוא על כהן גדול שמת שתהא מנחתו קריבה
משל ציבור. U-tenai beit din hu al Kohen Gadol she-met she-tehe minchato
kereva mi-shel tzibbur. But this is interesting because this, why to introduce
the phrase of תנאי בית דין tenai beit din here is not
so clear, it seems more similar to the previous ones. The כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol dies, the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol would bring a
מנחה mincha every day, half in the morning, half in the afternoon.
He dies. Who brings the מנחה? mincha? Now you could have said
nobody brings the מנחה, mincha, or the next- no, but it's in
this interim period where there is no כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. But
you could have said nobody. No, but somehow there was a תנאי
בית דין tenai beit din that you continue to bring the מנחה,
mincha, maybe that was part of the תנאי tenai even though the
קרבן korban wasn't mandated because there's no כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. Anyway,
they would bring it and they would bring it from communal funds.
רבי יהודה אומר משל יורשים, Rabbi Yehuda omer mi-shel yorshim, which is
a fascinating idea, the heirs of the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. So
the sense that if the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is dead and
before another one is appointed somehow it's still the dead כהן גדול's
Kohen Gadol responsibility. That's that is the implicit assumption. The dead כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol still has to make sure that this מנחה mincha
is brought. And when do you take him out of the category
of not being around or available? Right, he's available from the grave.
Something. And then it's only a question does it come from the
heirs or does it come from the ציבור. tzibbur. ושלמה היתה קריבה.
U-shelemah hayetah kereva. Now another statement of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is
although when the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol himself brings it it says
half in the morning and half in the afternoon, when it's brought
by the heirs, when he's dead and it's being brought for him,
it's brought as one unit not in two halves. So we'll see
about that in the גמרא. Gemara. So that's number four תקנה. takkanah.
על המלח ועל העצים שהכהנים נאותים בהם. Al ha-melach ve-al ha-etzim she-ha-kohanim
ne'otim ba-hem. Now this you understand the more the phrase of... תנאי
בית דין, tnai beis din, again, which sort of means like we
stipulate and allow the קדושה kedusha to follow our rules, as opposed
to the other stuff, which was more about where did the money
come from, because the כהנים kohanim can use the salt and the
wood in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Why they have salt and
wood? They had wood for the קרבנות korbanot and they had salt
because על כל קרבנך תקריב מלח. al kol korbandcha takriv melach. Okay,
but now I've gotten some meat from my חק chok from the
חטאת chatas and I want to eat it. Well, guess what two
things I'd like to use to eat my meat? I'd like some
firewood so I can roast it and I'd like some salt because
you want some salt on your meat. So they actually stipulated that
the salt and the wood that were for the קרבנות, korbanot, the
כהנים kohanim could actually use them for their for roasting the meat
and for, you know, for eating the meat of the קרבנות korbanot
that they're eating that they're themselves eating. They take a little הקדש.
hekdesh. Why isn't that מעילה? me'ilah? So now you understand this whole
תנאי בית דין tnai beis din which gives us this latitude to
sort of say the קדושה kedusha is going to work under, you
know, under the following rules. So we allow it that when you
want to use it for that purpose, then the it won't be
קדוש kadosh and you'll actually be allowed to use it for that
purpose. Okay. ועל הפרה שלא יהיו מועלים באפרה, ve'al haparah shelo ye'u
mo'alin be'afarah, באפרה, be'afarah, and with the פרה אדומה parah adumah that
there would not be מעילה me'ilah once it was burnt with the
ashes. We'll see what that's about. But isn't in the תורה Torah
basically what they're saying? Why? You mean because you use it for
sprinkling, but that doesn't prove there's no מעילה, me'ilah, like מצוות לאו
להנות ניתנו mitzvos lav lehanos nitnu and so on. Okay. ועל הקינים
הפסולות, ve'al hakinim hapsulot, now this refers to something we saw yesterday.
Let's say some of the birds that we brought, bought from the
money in the שופר, shofer, turned out to be invalid. שיהו באו
משל ציבור. shehu ba'u mishal tzibur. So the first answer is not
what we taught yesterday. The first thing is, you know, women put
in a hundred שקל shekel into this שופר. shofer. We have to
bring a hundred birds because of all their קרבנות. korbanot. We have
to make sure we bring it all today. They're going to assume
it's brought and for the end of the purification process and go
ahead and three of the birds we bought are no good. So
okay, but we have to bring three three more קרבנות korbanot for
those women. So where are we going to get the three birds
from? So the first answer is fine, we'll supply that with communal
funds. Okay, but clearly we have to make sure that all the
birds are brought. And the other stuff is what we said yesterday,
רבי יוסי אומר, Rebbi Yosi omer, no, no, no, no, no, we're
not going to get communal funds here, we're going to get the
supplier to pay for it. המספק את הקינים הוא מספק את הפסולות.
hamaspek es hakinim hu maspek es hapsulot. The guy who supplies the
birds, if any of the birds turn out to be פסול posul
or anything else, he'll he'll make, you know, he'll substitute good ones
for it. That's part of the conditions that we of the condition
we make for him to supply. So again, it is interesting, a
lot of these things are about where's the money coming from, but
the stuff in the middle about the salt and the wood is
what we've sort of used the idea of תנאי בית דין tnai
beis din more for in terms of stipulating how the קדושה kedusha
operates. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. רבי הושעיה רבה,
Rebbi Oshaya Rabba, רבי הושעיה Rebbi Oshaya the great or the elder,
אמר, amar, he said, לבוא בדמיהם שנו. lavo bidmeihem shanu. We're not
actually talking about bringing the animals themselves. We're talking about bringing their
money. Now what does that mean? Because here there's a problem here.
I mean, there's a couple of questions about this משנה. mishnah. Number
one is, you find this wandering animal. So one question is, I'm
going to bring it to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash to bring
it as an עולה. olah. Well, what if it's not really an
עולה? olah? I mean, what if it's חולין? chullin? Isn't that חולין
בעזרה? chullin ba'azarah? So I guess that you could solve and say,
okay, we'll be מקדיש makdish it as an עולה olah in case
it isn't an עולה, olah, we'll be מקדיש makdish it again. Or
maybe not. Maybe we just go by the numbers and the numbers
tell us it's an עולה olah and we don't try to cover
any bases. But there's also another question, which is, maybe it's a
שלמים. shlamim. If it's a male, who says it's an עולה? olah?
Maybe it's a שלמים. shlamim. So he wants to solve this problem
and say, okay, here's what we're going to do. We are going
to take this animal and we're not going to bring it itself.
What we're going to do is we're going to say, if this
animal is an עולה, olah, then I transfer the value of it
to this money and this money is sanctified as an עולה. olah.
And if not, I'll just סתם stam sanctify this money as an
עולה. olah. If it's a שלמים, shlamim, I'll transfer the value to
this other money. Okay, and if not, and then if not, then
I'll sanctify the money as a שלמים. shlamim. Then you bring one
שלמים shlamim and one עולה olah with the proceeds and one of
them represents the original animal and one of them will be a
new קרבן korban and you've got your bases covered. Now the problem
is there's a couple problems. Number one is the משנה mishnah doesn't
say that. The משנה mishnah says the animal itself and the משנה
mishnah doesn't sound like you have to cover your bases. But this
is what he's concerned about. So his initial explanation of the משנה
mishnah is לבוא בדמיהם. lavo bidmeihem. You're not going to bring the
animal itself. You're going to use the money that you're going to
transfer the קדושה kedusha to to bring a קרבן. korban. And the
only reason you'd want to do that is because it allows you
to bring both types of קרבנות korbanot and cover your bases. So
let's see what... but isn't this תמורה? tmurah? Like in other words...
no, no, you... oh, it's redeeming. You can redeem an animal on
money. No, the question you should ask is, you're allowed to normally
redeem an animal, a קרבן korban on money if what? Only if
there's a מום. mum. Only if there's a מום. mum. So that's
what the question's going to be. Okay, it's not תמורה, tmurah, it's
a problem of being פודה תמימים, podeh tmimim, right? So let's take
a look. Where does the money come from? Does you keep the
animal? So that's also not a good question. You, the finder? You
know, if you need to cover your bases, you'd want money here
that's הקדש hekdesh as well, but people would run away right away.
בית דין beis din would have to supply. the additional funds. Yeah,
so exactly. So anyway, let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara is
not going to be happy with this answer. So the גמרא Gemara
says אמר ליה רבי יוחנן. amar lei Rabbi Yochanan. So רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan says אומרין לו לאדם צא ומעול בקדשים? omrin lo l'adam
tze u'meal b'kodshim? Do we tell a person go and do מעילה
Meila with קדשים? Kodshim? Now the again the מפרשים Meforshim say he
doesn't literally mean מעילה, Meila, but what he means is how can
you redeem an animal without a מום? mum? That's a misuse of
קדשים. Kodshim. Since when are you allowed to do that? What type
of crazy suggestion is that? אלא הכא מנח אחרי הרוב. ella hacha
manach acharei harov. You go by the majority. None of this playing
cover your bases and you're doing it with money. The משנה Mishnah
doesn't say an עולה Olah and a שלמים. Shelamim. It says an
עולה. Olah. You bring the thing itself. You go by the majority.
Now presumably רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is still bothered with this question
of how do you though know that the males are עולות? olas?
Maybe the males are also שלמים. shelamim. So he gives the following
additional scenario to the משנה Mishnah to help answer that question. אם
רוב זכרים עולה אם רוב נקבות זבחי שלמים. im rov zecharim olah
im rov nekeivot zivchei shelamim. So it says if most of the
animals, and this is the way some of the מפרשים meforshim read
it, okay, if most you found actually like a flock of animals.
Whoever said you found a flock of animals I don't know. You
found a group of animals. If the majority of them are male,
then you could already assume that you're dealing with עולות. olos. Why
would you have so many male animals wandering around unless they were
and they were עולה? olah? Which is a very funny question. So
the גמרא Gemara is not going to be happy with this. So
what happens if you find just one animal? Yeah, it doesn't tell
you. Maybe then I don't know. Anyway again we're all struggling with
this of why do we assume it's an עולה olah but the
answers are less than satisfying. So the גמרא Gemara says ואין שלמים
באין מן הזכרים ומן הנקבות. v'ein shelamim ba'in min hazecharim u'min haneikeivot.
So the גמרא Gemara says well what are you talking about? Whether
it's males, most are male, most are female, they can still, a
שלמים shelamim could still be from a male. Okay, so כיצד הוא
עושה? keitzad hu oseh? So what do you do in order to
sort of solve this problem of maybe it's an עולה olah maybe
it's a שלמים? shelamim? מוציאן לחולין וחוזר ועושה אותן עולות. motzi'an l'chullin
v'chozer v'oseh osan olot. You take it out to חולין Chullin and
then you go back and make them עולות. olos. So what back
does that mean? I gotta tell you. Like the מפרשים meforshim say
well maybe you are פודה podeh them תמימים, tmimim, but although you're
normally not allowed to redeem anything without a blemish, if you're here
you're going to resanctify it. So what you do is you say
if it's an עולה olah I transfer the קדושה Kedusha to this
money. If it's a שלמים shelamim I transfer it to this. This
money either way is going to be עולה. olah. Either because I
transferred the קדושה Kedusha or I sanctified it. And now I say
and
now I transfer the קדושה Kedusha back to the animal.
And now the animal it gets back to being an עולה. olah.
The other money, the שלמים shelamim though? The other money I have
to buy something. So first of all we introduced that there's other
money I gotta buy שלמים. shelamim. Number two is
it's all very nice that at the end of the day this
animal is back to being an עולה. olah. But we have never
heard of such a thing that you're allowed to redeem an unblemished
animal if at the end of the day you'll get it back
to where it came from. So it's a very unclear what the
גמרא Gemara's answer is. It is bothered why we assume it's an
עולה olah and not a שלמים shelamim but the answer here is
quite hard to understand. You know and the מפרשים meforshim really sort
of grapple with it. Okay, so some want to say that that
wasn't an answer, that that was part of the question. What do
you want him to do? Do you want him to be מוציא
motzi it לחולין l'chullin and go back and make it an עולה?
olah? So you know if you don't like the answer you turn
it into a rhetorical question. Okay, but anyway but it is a
big issue about what answer this was. Okay. So now we have
an answer which is a little bit more satisfying. So let's take
a look. We still don't have a good answer. But now let's
see because again maybe it is a שלמים shelamim and you can't
redeem it if it's unblemished and anyway the משנה mishnah doesn't say
to redeem it. So let's take a look. אמר רבי זירא amar
Rabbi Zeira כמה דאת אמר תמן. k'ma d'at amar taman. Here's going
to be our answer. The same way we said over there תנאי
בית דין הוא על המותרות שיקרבו עולות. tnai Beis Din hu al
hamotarot sheyikrevu olos. Remember the thing we said before that if you
have leftover money from a חטאת chatas and an אשם asham or
whatever we stipulate and we say that that leftover money gets applied
to the נדבה, nedava, gets applied to the עולה olah fund, right?
We've been learning that the last two days. All of this leftover
money if you have a doubt about a שקל shekel or the
שקל shekel the guy died. What do you do with it? נדבה.
nedava. נדבה. nedava. You put it in the עולה olah fund. So
says that, that solves our problems here too. We don't know if
it's a שלמים shelamim or an עולה. olah. So we could say
ah, the בית דין Beis Din stipulates that if you have a
doubt we use the then you find this lost animal. You got
a doubt שלמים shelamim or עולה. olah. It becomes an עולה. olah.
Just like everything else when we have a doubt becomes an עולה.
olah. Okay, so שיקרבו עולות. sheyikrevu olos. The same way we say
that about leftover money for a חטאת chatas and an אשם asham
כמה דאת אמר והכא k'ma d'at amar v'hacha you say the same
thing here תנאי בית דין הוא על אבודות שיקרבו עולות. tnai Beis
Din hu al avodot sheyikrevu olos. בית דין Beis Din stipulates if
you've got a lost animal and you don't know if it's an
עולה olah or a שלמים, shelamim, male animal, then therefore you don't
know if it's an עולה olah or a שלמים. shelamim. Okay, it
becomes an עולה. olah. So again we get to make the rule
and we get to stipulate how the heck this is going to
work. At least this rule is consistent with what we've seen before
which is when you have certain doubts and certain questions and leftover
money it goes to the עולה olah fund and this same type
of thing
happens. אמר רבי יוסי לרבי יעקב בר אחא. amar Rabbi Yossi l'Rabbi
Yaakov bar Acha. אין זה מזיד? ein zeh meizid? Is this not
a מזיד? meizid? So meaning how can you willingly go ahead and
actively be a... I mean in all the other cases you... is,
you know, there was leftover money, it was some other type of
the thing. Here, this is an active reapplying of something that could
be a שלמים shlamim into an עולה. olah. אמר ליה קשיא, Amar
leh kashya,
the same as...
yeah, I mean it's a little bit unclear like what are you
asking that we don't already know. Anyway, אמר ליה, amar leh, מכיוון
דתנאי בית דין אין זה מזיד. mideka tna'ei beis din ain ze
meizid. Maybe he was asking how the rabbis are allowed to do
such a thing. And the answer is: no, it's all part of
the rules. Since it's part of the rules, there's nothing wrong with
doing it. Okay, so we get to stipulate at the beginning, anybody
who sanctifies an animal, you are implicitly buying into all of the
following conditions and stipulations and rules whether you're aware of them or
not. Okay, and then we get and then what you know, under
those circumstances, we get to say what happens to it. It really
is like a much, much, much more expanded idea of כל המקדש
אדעתא דרבנן מקדש, kol hamikadesh ada'ata derabanan mikadesh, which Michael quipped was
כל המקדיש אדעתא דרבנן מקדיש. kol hamakdish ada'ata derabanan makdish. Okay. אמר
רבי יוסי, Amar Rabbi Yosei, עד דאנה תמן, ad d'ana taman, so
again, this same phrase from אמר רבי יוסי. Amar Rabbi Yosei. Was
the first time we had it was it אמר רבי יוסי? Amar
Rabbi Yosei? I don't think so. But he says when I was
there, when I was still there in בבל, Bavel, עד דאנה תמן,
ad d'ana taman, when I was still there, שמעת קליה דרבי
יהודה שאל לשמואל. shamas kol Rabbi Yehuda shaal leShmuel. Again, it's always
the same. I heard the sound of Rabbi Yehuda asking Shmuel. We
had exactly that same phrase before. Okay.
And here is the question he asked: הפריש שקלו ומת. hifrish shekalo
umes. So now this is exactly what we quoted earlier. I mean,
so not only is the idiom of when I was there I
heard the sound, this is actually a direct quote of what we
said earlier, right? What happens if the guy separated his שקל, shekel,
didn't give it, and then dropped dead? What do you do with
that money? הפריש
שקלו ומת, hifrish shekalo umes, so what's the הלכה? halacha? And then
Shmuel said back to him, אמר ליה יפלו לנדבה. amar leh yiplu
l'nedava. Same type of thing we're saying here, you got some problems,
throw it into the נדבה nedava fund. Okay, now, ומותר עשירית האיפה
שלו. umosar asiris haeifa shelo. So what if the כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol has sanctified money for to use for his עשירית האיפה, asiris
haeifa, which is his regular daily קרבן korban as we've mentioned in
the משנה, Mishna, half in the morning half in the afternoon, and
there's leftover funds? What do you do with those leftover funds? Okay,
so there Rabbi Yochanan אומר יוליכם לים המלח. omer yolichem l'Yam HaMelach.
That doesn't go into the נדבה, nedava, that gets thrown into the
ים המלח. Yam HaMelach. Not exactly clear why it's different than something
like a שקל shekel or whatnot,
but that gets thrown. Maybe because most of the things that we
wind up putting into the נדבה nedava fund are either from communal
or from a חטאת chatas and an אשם. asham. This is neither
communal nor a חטאת chatas or אשם. asham. Of course, as we
just learned before about the animal wandering around, we are really not
limited to what types of things we get to say go into
automatically become an עולה olah or go into the עולה olah fund.
רבי אליעזר אומר יפלו לנדבה. Rabbi Eliezer omer yiplu l'nedava. That's why...
did Rabbi Yehuda say משל יורשין? mishal yorshin? No, no, no, that's
not this.
That's when he
died and the question is who's going to now bring the new
one. This is leftover money. He's not dead. He sanctified money to
bring his עשירית האיפה asiris haeifa and then there is leftover funds.
I understand, you said for tomorrow.
Oh no, he is dead, because otherwise you're right, he would use
it for tomorrow. So he is dead. Okay. No, no, no, no,
but this is the question of what to do with the funds
that were already sanctified. Meaning the question in the משנה Mishna is
there's no money sanctified but we assume we have to keep on
bringing the קרבן. korban. Okay, here you have sanctified funds that cannot
be used for this purpose, what are you going to do with
them? Of course, you're saying, "Hey, if the משנה Mishna assumes we
keep on bringing the קרבן, korban, bring it after he's dead." Yeah,
maybe there's now a new כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, so a new
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is bringing it with his money. Okay. So
there Rabbi Yochanan says throw it ים המלח, Yam HaMelach, interesting why
that's different than the normal rule or what we've or the common
thing we've been seeing, and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says what we've
been seeing by most other things: יפלו לנדבה. yiplu l'nedava. Okay. Now.
Now we get to another issue about how to use what to
do with this money with the
normal way in which the עשירית האיפה asiris haeifa of the כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol was brought before we get into sort of problems.
Let's take a look. Okay, so עשירית האיפה של כהן גדול. asiris
haeifa shel Kohen Gadol. Now that we're talking about it, we mentioned
it here if he sanctified money and he died, we mentioned in
the משנה Mishna what do you do when he's already dead, what
do you bring? Let's talk about this עשירית האיפה. asiris haeifa.
Rabbi Yochanan אומר חוצה אותה ואחר כך מקדשה. omer chotzah osah v'achar
kach mekadeshah. First you make the whole איפה eifa in a non-כלי
שרת, kli shares, then you divide it into two halves because it
says מחציתה בבוקר ומחציתה בערב, machatzisah baboker umachatzisah ba'erev, and only after
you make it into two halves do you put each half in
a כלי שרת. kli shares. Okay, if you remember this is somewhat
similar to the discussion of like how did you make the קטורת.
ketores. Did you originally make it in a כלי שרת kli shares
or not? At what stage did you introduce the כלי שרת kli
shares and did it become sanctified? So Rabbi Yochanan says only after
you made it and then divided it in two. ריש לקיש אמר
מקדשה ואחר כך חוצה אותה. Resh Lakish omer mekadeshah v'achar chotzah osah.
No, you make it all together in a כלי שרת kli shares
and then you divide it and it's already sanctified from the beginning.
Okay, now we're going to try to prove one side or the
other. מתניתא פליגא על רבי יוחנן. Masnisa peliga al Rabbi Yochanan. The
following
משנה Mishna argues on Rabbi Yochanan.
Or ברייתא, braisa, excuse me: מקריב מחצה ומחצה אבד. makriv mechtzo umechtzo
avad.
So you bring half and half gets thrown out. Which means what?
This is the scenario in which... let me just double check here.
Oh, so what happens is half of no, no, we'll get to
that in a minute. The כהן גדול Kohen Gadol brought half in
the morning, and then the other half got טמא. tamei. Okay, so
what do you do with the other half? But you still have
to bring a half in the afternoon. So you could say, okay,
make another half, but the תורה Torah the way it describes it
is it has to be defined as the half, okay, not just...
So what you do is you make another whole, you divide it
in half, okay, you bring half, okay, and the other half has
to go to waste, okay. So מחצה מקריב ומחצה אבד mechtza makriv
u-mechtza avad and the other half goes to waste. Now the question
is why does the other half have to go to waste? According
to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, you don't sanctify it until you divide
it into halves. So make the whole, divide into half, sanctify one,
and the other half don't sanctify and it doesn't have to go
to waste. So that's a pretty good proof against רבי יוחנן. Rabbi
Yochanan. So פתר לה patar la you can explain it שכן אפילו
מעות ילכו לים המלח. she-ken afilu ma'os yelchu l'Yam HaMelach.
So even the money would go to ים המלח, Yam HaMelach, which
means what? Hold on a minute.
Ah,
because רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said, and this is how it ties
in a minute ago, that what happens if the כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol sets aside money and there's leftover money from the עשירית האיפה?
asiris ha-eifa? What does he say you do with it? Right? Remember,
he said you throw it to ים המלח. Yam HaMelach. So he
said even though that wasn't sanctified in a כלי שרת, kli shares,
right, it doesn't matter. Once it has the sanctity of the עשירית
האיפה asiris ha-eifa even without the כלי שרת, kli shares, if you
can't use it, you have to dispose of it. So this is
no different. It's not like it wasn't sanctified at all. It still
had קדושת פה kedushas peh like the money you would sanctify, it
just didn't have the קדושה kedusha of the כלי שרת. kli shares.
So that isn't a question to him. He says even without the
כלי שרת, kli shares, if you can't use it, it goes to
ים המלח. Yam HaMelach.
בתוך כלי שרת be-soch kli shares saying that there's a כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol who was מקדיש makdish it for today? Like that's, you
know, the first case of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says ילכו לים
המלח. yelchu l'Yam HaMelach. So he was מקדיש makdish it for today.
For some reason you can't use it for tomorrow. Why would that
be?
That I don't know. Okay, that I don't know. He did before,
as you point out, say ומת, u-meis, so then maybe you could...
oh you mean... oh... oh you mean
once it's in a כלי שרת kli shares won't use it for
tomorrow because of לינה? lina? No, no, the money you could use
for tomorrow if he didn't die, but the actual... if you're asking
why this actual מנחה, mincha, the second half that's leftover can't be
used for tomorrow, that's because of לינה. lina. And probably also what...
you can't just keep it...
Okay, it might also be that it's not the half... it's not
a pair with the other half that's also going to be brought.
I don't know, I'd have to look into that. Okay. Now so
that anyway that seemed to be a contradiction to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi
Yochanan, but in the end okay, it wasn't a כלי שרת, kli
shares, you still have to go ahead and dispose of it. Even
money would be the same. Now מתניתין פליגא matnisin pliga now here
argues against רבי שמעון בן לקיש, Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish, but all
the מפרשים meforshim switched this to
רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. It's another contradiction to רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan.
Let's take a look. נמצאו שני חצאין קרבים ושני חצאין אבודין. nimtze'u
shnei chatza'in krevim u-shnei chatza'in avudin. There's a scenario in which two
halves will be brought and two halves will have to go to
waste. What's the scenario? So this is a case where one כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol dies in the morning after his first half was
brought and another one is appointed in the afternoon. So the other
one has to bring his קרבן. korban. So he makes a whole
and he brings his half in the afternoon. So the half that's
leftover from the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol in the morning and the
half of the new כהן, Kohen, all of those have to get,
you know, can't be used. The two halves are brought and two
halves are thrown out. Okay, ותני עלה, v'sani ala, we taught on
it,
מחצה ראשון ומחצה שני תעובר צורתן ויצאו לבית השרפה. mechtza rishon u-mechtza
sheni te'uber tzurasan v'yeitzu l'veis ha-sreifa. So what do you do with
them? The two halves, whether it's the first כהן Kohen or the
second כהן, Kohen, you have to wait until they're פסול בלינה, pasul
b'lina, right? You don't dispose of them while they're still קדוש, kadosh,
whatever, you know, while the קדושה kedusha has, you know, even if
you can't be מקריב makriv them, you don't dispose of them, but
by the next day they're פסול בלינה, pasul b'lina, then you go
ahead and you burn them. So this is more of a problem
because this is not just like ים המלח. Yam HaMelach. This is
you have to wait until they're פסול בלינה pasul b'lina and it's
יצאו לבית השרפה, yeitzu l'veis ha-sreifa, which sounds like it really has
the full קדושה kedusha that can't be used. So it sounds like
you did it in a כלי שרת. kli shares. Why do you
have to do the second guy's one, the second half, in a
כלי שרת? kli shares? So the גמרא Gemara says
פתר לה patar la like
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael דאמר d'amar איסרון מקדש isaron mekadesh כשהכהן מתקרב
תחילה. keshe-ha-kohen miskarev techila. Now there's a question if the next line
sort of is part of this statement or not, but he would
sanctify the איסרון, isaron, which is not exactly clear how that's an
answer because still the question is about where, you know, it's nice
that he sanctified it, but why did it... was it necessarily with
a כלי שרת? kli shares? Let me just hold on, double check
the קרבנות העדה Korbanos HaEida on this. One minute.
Yeah, so basically what he says like this is he says, which
then sort of completely eliminates all the difference, is that when you
measured out the amount of flour, you measured it out in a
כלי שרת, kli shares, so that even רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan agrees
that really the stuff got sanctified earlier on in the process in
a כלי שרת, kli shares, which is now completely... it's completely undermines
the difference between רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish.
I mean if you sanctified it at one stage even before, you
know, in a כלי שרת... kli shares... and who cares if when
you then, so anyway, so the קרבן העדה Korban Ha-Eda says, well
he would agree that לכתחילה l'chatchila you start in a כלי שרת.
kli shares. All רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan was saying was that בדיעבד
b'diavad it was okay to wait until you got around to divide
it. But everybody would certainly agree לכתחילה l'chatchila you always start with
a כלי שרת kli shares and anyway therefore so goodbye any real
difference between them because we could always answer everything that you did
it the לכתחילה l'chatchila way. Okay, but that obviously on the face
of it is a very good evidence as is the that you
would always start out fully sanctified even before you divided it into
attavs. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara moves on to another
question. Okay, כשכהן מתקרב תחלה לעבודה. keshekohein mitkarev techila la'avoda. Now when
a כהן kohein normally forget כהן גדול kohein gadol any כהן kohein
when they when they begin the עבודה avoda how do they get
initiated into the עבודה avoda in the תורה Torah it speaks about
this whole process right about with the oil and the whole like
חנוכת המשכן Chanukat Hamishkan and with the חנוכה Chanuka of the כהן
kohein of the כהנים kohanim as well you know how they were
sort of sanctified in their role. The גמרא Gemara says after that
time though the way a כהן kohein is sanctified in his role
is that when he begins his role he brings a עשירית האיפה.
asirit ha-eifa. Okay like the כהן גדול kohein gadol would bring every
day the first time. כשכהן מתקרב תחלה לעבודה מביא עשירית האיפה שלו.
Keshekohein mitkarev techila la'avoda meivi asirit ha-eifa shelo. Okay now ועובדה בידו
v'ovda beyado not only would he bring it but he would actually
be מקריב makriv it. So that would be his first act that
would initiate him into the role of a כהן kohein in the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. אחד כהן גדול ואחד כהן הדיוט שעבדו עד
שלא הביאו עשירית האיפה שלהן Echad kohein gadol v'echad kohein hedyot she'avdu
ad shelo heviu asirit ha-eifa shelahen let's say בדיעבד b'diavad they ran
in to do the עבודה avoda without bringing their עשירית האיפה asirit
ha-eifa how much was this absolutely necessary to give him his status
as a כהן kohein so
עבודתן כשירה avodatan keshera בדיעבד b'diavad the עבודה avoda is כשר kasher
although some have the גרסא girsa פסולה. psula. Okay right the הגר"א'ס
G'ra's גרסא girsa is פסולה. psula. Okay slight little difference. Okay but
basically everybody would start with this עשירית האיפה asirit ha-eifa and if
you didn't do it that might or might not depending on your
גרסא girsa impact whether the עבודה avoda was כשר kasher בדיעבד b'diavad
or not. Now רבי מני בעי Rabbi Mani ba'i רבי מני Rabbi
Mani asked מימר בו ביום שנתקרב תחלה לעבודה בו ביום נתמנה להיות
כהן גדול meimar bo bayom shenitkarev techila la'avoda bo bayom nimna liyot
kohein gadol let's say a guy was very fortunate the first day
he was going to start working as a כהן kohein was also
the day he was appointed as a כהן גדול kohein gadol so
you're wonder how did this little פישר pisher who never worked before
get to be the כהן גדול kohein gadol who knows maybe it
was יחוס yichus maybe it was money but that very same day
so now he has two עשירית האיפה'ס asirit ha-eifas to bring right
he has the עשירית האיפה asirit ha-eifa to bring as every new
כהן kohein that begins the עבודה avoda brings an עשירית האיפה asirit
ha-eifa and as a כהן גדול kohein gadol he brings a regular
עשירית האיפה. asirit ha-eifa. Okay so מביא שתים meivi shtayim he brings
two אחת לחינוכו ואחת לחובת היום achat l'chinucho v'achat l'chovat hayom one
for his initiation as a כהן kohein and the other for his
daily obligation. Now that seems to be a statement not a question
but it might be a question would he have to bring two
could he use his regular one to also count as his initiating
one or not. Okay so it's made here as a statement but
it says בעי ba'i so maybe it is that is what's being
asked. Okay we'll just read one more thing תופיני tufinei now when
the תורה Torah discusses how it's made it says תופיני מנחת פתים.
tufinei minchat pitim. So what does the word תופיני tufinei mean so
בשעת הבאה תופיני besha'at hava'a tufinei ואין בשחרית תופיני. v'ein beshachris tufinei.
So at the time of bringing it it should be baked and
there is not a תופיני tufinei in the morning which basically
means that you don't bake it at night so you only you
know or תני Tanni says בשחרית beshachris but meaning you don't it's
so it's it has to be baked once it's already fit to
be
brought. Apparently the way the מפרשים meforshim it is is when you
bake this מנחה, mincha, right, when do you bake it, so they're
somehow reading, maybe it's because of the end of the פסוק pasuk
is תופיני מנחת פתים תקריב, tufinei minchat pitim takriv, so it has
to be baked at the time of הקרבה hakrava and you can't
bake it, it can't be fresh in the morning, which means that
it was baked the night before. Okay, it has to be baked
the day, that's how the מפרשים meforshim are reading this. והתנינן v'ha
t'ninan but did we not teach העמידו עושי חביתין לעשות חביתין he'emidu
osei chavitin la'asot chavitin that the announcement went out and we talked
in מדות middos remember when we talked about everybody's different role that
one of the guys had the job in the before daybreak to
say everybody who's making you know the חביתין chavitin you know who's
baking it this is the חביתין chavitin was the phrase of the
כהן גדול'ס kohein gadol's עשירית האיפה asirit ha-eifa get up to start
baking it. And this is when it's still dark outside like we
know bakers wake up at 4:00 AM right so look it sounds
like it was baked the night before. Oh exactly.
אמר רבי חייא בר אבא
Amar Rabbi
Chiya bar Abba לעשות
חמים לריבוכה לרכבה. la'asot chamim lerivucha lirachva. Anyway no it means to
heat up the water heat up the fire not to actually begin
baking it we'll wait to bake it until the actual morning itself.
Okay we'll continue with this tomorrow.